Part 3.35 levels of a performance creative. Okay,
this is actually really important. Um,
I broke this down because these are the different layers of skillsets that I've
learned over the years that have made me, let's say the,
the strategists and the creative perfor, uh, creative entrepreneur I've become.
Okay, so level one is editing. All right? Editing or design. Uh,
I didn't include design, but I started off as a graphic designer in Photoshop,
right? So when you, when you just know editing,
you understand the programs and the tools, how to cut, you know,
how to cut with, with provided assets and follow a script, basically, you know,
you're told what to do and you know you can go and do it. Level two,
I would say, is when you can con combine videography and editing.
Now you're kind of like more self-sufficient. You know,
you have more vision of what the video's gonna look like, uh,
in post-production, especially if you are shooting it,
you know what you're gonna edit. At least when I'm shooting, I was like, oh,
I can use that cut. Oh, I can definitely use that cut. Oh, that's not good.
Versus when you're just editing and you're seeing the footage for the first
time, you don't have the context, you don't have the nuances that you know,
that you get when you're onset or you're shooting it. And, you know,
when you're shooting a video, you have the,
you have the intention of of editing it a certain way.
So when you combine those two, I think you have much more, uh,
uh, you're more grounded for sure. Next,
I would say level three is adding copywriting to the mix.
You now understand the customer avatar and you can script a video that resonates
more deeply with an audience. Obviously, it's kind of like backwards.
'cause I feel like copywriting is the start of the, of the creative process,
or at least scripting and copywriting,
which then sets the tone for the rest of the video. And, um,
if you're an editor who knows copywriting, I think this is a super,
super valuable skill that very few editors have. Uh,
if you can write your own copy and edit, boom,
you've just eliminated the need for a copywriter.
So I'm not the best copywriter, but I can definitely like write my own stuff.
Um, and you know, it, it just makes things a lot more efficient.
You don't have to wait for anybody to provide you copy. And it's like, okay,
I can just make this up on the spot. And, uh,
if English is your second language, it, it might be more challenging.
But even then you can still learn.
You can still learn some of the basics because that's gonna help you a ton.
Especially 'cause there's so much, so much text and so much writing in,
in editing. And if you're not decent at it, it's gonna be more of a struggle.
Alright, next level four is adding directing to the mix.
You now can elicit a strong,
authentic emotional response in the creative that will resonate with the
audience at a much deeper level. If you don't get the chance to direct,
I definitely suggest doing some of your own projects, directing your own talent,
because when you direct talent, you,
you can feel the energy and the performance going back and forth from,
from the actor or whoever you're working with. Like, oh no, I don't like that.
Like, let's do it again. That doesn't sound authentic. Let's do it again. Uh,
tell me about a time where you actually felt, you know, mad about something.
I wanna see more of that, or I'm not believing it.
Can you tell it in your own words? Like,
these are all things that I've learned as a director, uh,
to be able to elicit a stronger emotion outta people.
'cause sometimes actors definitely need to be directed if they're self-directed.
Like let's say they're shooting u G C at home or, um, you know,
shooting their own content,
they don't have someone judging them based off their performance.
They're just kind of going with, I think that's good.
But when you have the eye to be able to discern, okay, that was,
that was believable, that wasn't believable.
Sometimes I actors don't have that self-awareness yet. So when you,
when you become a director, when you start directing your own stuff,
you can manage the quality much more effectively. Sometimes you just can't.
'cause sometimes talent isn't as good as you'd hope them to be, and that's okay,
you just don't work with them again. But I would say it's a very,
very valuable skill. And when you direct you,
you know what to extract from the actor that will
later go into the video. Like, it's like, okay, I need you to say this,
this line, say this line, say it five different ways, and then boom.
Now I have five different variations in editing, which, you know,
takes very little time when you're directing versus, you know,
if you're not, if you, if you don't have that luxury. Okay, level five,
last one is strategy and media. Now, if you have all these components,
you have a fully comprehensive understanding from ideation to iteration,
and you're able to refine and improve any stage of the creative process. Okay?
This, this shows that you have done everything from design,
editing, copywriting, videography, editing, and now even launching your own ads.
This is a long journey, okay?
There's a lot of different skill sets and nuances required to learn all of
those. But when you learn that you can most definitely be
your own creative entrepreneur,
you can be a creative strategist in a company,
you can manage a big team, um, you'll have,
people are gonna come to you for advice and for help and solutions,
which means a higher responsibility level, which means higher income.
And I would say, uh, this is something that I've had to learn,
not forcibly, but, you know, I had,
I had to learn it because I didn't have a choice.
It's not something that I wanna do every day,
but when you just know how it works, it's enough. Okay?
So it's not like I'm gonna focus all of my stuff in media buying because that's
not my strength. My strength lies in editing and directing and creating content.
Um,
but I know how to talk to media buyers and I know how to talk to strategists
about, um, the direction.
And so I'm able to execute much more effectively that way.